It is כ"ו Chaf Vav and we pick up, we're actually more
or less caught up and we pick up at the very bottom
of כ"ו עמוד ב' Chaf Vav Amud Beis
with the following. We're working through what the שניות לעריות Shnios L'Arayos
are and we are... שלח ליה רב משרשיא מתוסניא לרב פפי, Shlach
Lei Rav Mesharshiya MiTusnaya L'Rav Pappi, Tusnaya is Tunisia maybe, no not
really, Rav Pappi, so the line towards פפי Pappi it is five
lines before the lines get wide.
ילמדנו רבינו, Yalmdenu Rabbeinu, let our master teach us אשת אחי אבי
האב, Eshet Achi Avi Ha'av, so we worked through what the שניות
Shnios was and we had a little bit of a discussion about,
well a little anyway, a discussion about which ones יש להם הפסק
Yesh Lahem Hefsek or אין להם הפסק, Ein Lahem Hefsek, continue to
go through multiple variations, multiple generations
and now we're going to continue to flesh out the list. So
אשת אחי אבי האב ואחות אבי האב מהו?
Eshet Achi Avi
Ha'av V'achot Avi Ha'av Mahu?
The wife of the grandfather's brother, the great uncle, or the sister
of the grandfather, so either way it's the great aunt. Okay, what's
the story? Now we've already discussed, here we get to use our
new board here, okay we've already discussed that you've got, that you
have the case of, okay here's you, here's
you.
So this is אב, Av, okay this is your brother, אחיו של
אב מן האם, Achiv shel Av min Ha'em, okay now when you
say
here's you, okay this is your, this is your uncle on your
mother's side, okay this is your, this is your, okay
this is your brother, sorry, who's the second?
Okay, that's
your uncle on your mother's side. Okay, so these cases דאורייתא De'oraisa
really the only one would be the case about your, okay, a
case about your father's brother on your father's side. Okay,
so here if you have, anyway,
here the only one that would be דאורייתא De'oraisa would be your
father's brother on your mother's side, his wife. Okay, but Rabbinically here
we've got
your uncle related through your maternal uncle, anyway your father's maternal
brother and your mother's brother. Those would be the
שניות Shnios and their wives, obviously their wives. Okay
anyway so you've got your aunts, you've got your aunts that are
not the normal case of the aunts. The normal case in the
aunts that are in the תורה Torah are basically father's... the wife
would have made
it even more complicated.
Anyway,
those are the case of the שניות. Shnios. Okay now what we
want to know is, what we want to know is אשת אחי
אבי האב ואחות אבי האב. Eshet Achi Avi Ha'av V'achot Avi Ha'av.
So we've got ואחות, V'achot, so we want to deal with your
grandfather, okay these are the cases we've already identified here are שניות,
Shnios, either your mother's brother's wife or your father's brother's wife on
your maternal brother. What about your grandfather's
wife and what is it
אשת אחי אבי האב ואחות אבי האב? Eshet Achi Avi Ha'av V'achot
Avi Ha'av? Okay, so you've either got your grandfather's sister, okay that's
one type of aunt, or your grandfather's brother's wife, אח. Ach.
Okay,
so basically it's your aunt going straight up.
All right, so that's your great aunt, what's the story? Okay, so
מהו, Mahu, what's the story? I don't know if drawing that made
it at all clear or made it worse, but anyway.
One line, isn't it exactly?
We're about five lines before the lines get wide. What's the story
about your great aunt? מדילמטה ערווה למעלה נמי גזרו בה? Midelemata Erva
Lemala Nami Gazru Bah? Do we say that since directly one below
it's an ערווה, Erva, meaning because if it were a case of
your father's, right, it would be just directly above all of these
cases, maybe make this easier, okay
let's take a look. If it were these cases in case of
your father, your father's sister, so here's your aunt because it's your
father's sister, okay and here's an aunt because it is your father's
brother's wife, right? Those cases are straight דאורייתא ערווה, De'oraisa Erva, okay
that's אב Av and aunts. Those are דאורייתא ערווה. De'oraisa Erva.
This is the exact same case except it's with your grandfather, a
generation removed.
So what do we say? What do we say? This is that
easy. What do we say? מהו? Mahu? מדלמטה Midilmata ערווה, ervah, since
one generation below that exact scenario is an ערווה, ervah, למעלה נמי
נגזור ביה. l'ma'ala nami nigzor bei. So when it's a grandfather they
also made the גזירה? gzera? או דלמא, O dilma, or do we
say,
האי פליג דרא, hai palig dara, the generations have gotten too distant.
If it's going to start with a grandfather we're not going to
make it a problem. Okay, now it's a little bit funny because
in the פסק p'sak we talked about אין לה הפסק ein la
hefsek and so on, so that doesn't seem to usually bother the
גמרא, Gemara, let's see what it says. Okay,
so תא שמע, ta shma, מאי הן השניות? mai hen hashniyos? The
משנה, Mishna, הברייתא haBraitah we had yesterday listed the שניות, shniyos, ולא
קחשיב להו בהדיא, v'lo kachashiv lehu behadya, and it didn't list great-aunts
in it. So the גמרא Gemara says, alright, תנא ושייר, tana v'shayer,
it left things off the list. It's not a complete list. You
can't prove anything from things that aren't listed. מאי שייר דהאי שייר?
mai shayer d'hai shayer? What else did it leave off the list?
So שייר שניות דבי רבי חייא, shayer shniyos d'bei Rabbi Chiya, the
שניות shniyos of Rabbi Chiya, which we're going to see in a
minute. Charlie has a whole chart for us. So there's other things
left off the list. So we don't know the answer. We don't
know what to say about great-aunts. So
אמימר Amemar אכשר achshar באשת אחי אבי אביו ובאחות אבי אביו. b'eishet
achi avi aviv u'bachot avi aviv. He allowed great-aunts. So אמר ליה
רב הלל לרב אשי, amar lei Rav Hillel l'Rav Ashi, so רב
הלל Rav Hillel said to רב אשי, Rav Ashi, לדידי חזי לי
בשניות מר בריה דרבנא, l'didi chazi li b'shniyos Mar brei de-Ravna,
I saw a list of secondary עריות arayos from מר בריה דרבנא,
Mar brei de-Ravna, וכתיבן שיתסר לאיסורא, u'chtivan shitser l'issura, and there it
said that there are sixteen secondary עריות. arayos. So what can those
sixteen be? מאי לאו, mai lav, is it not תמני דמתניתין, tamni
d'matnitin, the eight we listed in the ברייתא braita that we were
discussing yesterday, ושית דבי רבי חייא, v'shit d'bei Rabbi Chiya, we're going
to see Rabbi Chiya has six, that gets us up to fourteen.
So that's fourteen. What could the other two be? It said that
there are sixteen. So הנך תרתי, hanach tarti, it must be the
other two that we haven't covered in either yesterday's list or the
list we're going to see in a minute of Rabbi Chiya, must
be these two about great-aunts. והא שיתסר, v'ha shitser, that would make
sixteen. So from that we can infer that the great-aunts are included.
The גמרא Gemara says, ולטעמיך, u'l'ta'amecha, according to your reasoning, שבעסר הויין,
shivsar havyan, it should be seventeen. Why? Because we actually yesterday added
an additional one that wasn't in the original list of eight. What
additional one did we add? דאיכא אשת אחי האם מן האם. d'ika
eishet achi ha'em min ha'em. We added your mother's brother
on the maternal side, so there's no fathers involved. Your mother's maternal
brother's wife, so your aunt, but your aunt only because it is
all through mothers, your mother's maternal brother's wife. And that we thought
maybe not, but yesterday we concluded that was a problem. So that
got us up to an additional one. So according to the way
you want to count, you got seventeen, not sixteen. So you're not
going to get your sixteen anyway. דפשטינא מאיסורא, d'pashtina m'issura, we concluded
yesterday was forbidden. The גמרא Gemara says, הא לא קשיא, ha lo
kashya, that's not difficult. הנך תרתי דדמיין להדדי כחדא חשיב להו. hanach
tarti d'damyan l'hadadi k'chada chashiv lehu.
The two that are similar were counted only as one. What two
are similar? The בית רש"י beis Rashi tells us, or just say
רש"י, Rashi, it's easy enough. He basically says the two we're talking
about, which is two types of great-aunt, your grandfather's sister or your
grandfather's brother's wife, that would count as one. It's two versions of
great-aunt and it's all on the father's side. You do that about
a lot of these things. Alright, that's true. Anyway, the point is
I could get sixteen, but if I add great-aunt. So I think
we should be adding great-aunt because that'll get us up to the
number sixteen that we saw, and I saw the number sixteen in
this list. So the גמרא Gemara says, והא שיתסר, v'ha shitser, that
would make sixteen. The גמרא Gemara says, והא מכל מקום לדידי חזי
לי דכתיבן לאיסורא, v'ha mikol makom l'didi chazi li d'chtivan l'issura, and
I saw it said sixteen are forbidden, and I was able and
I can add these two of great-aunts, count them as two, count
them as one, and I can get us up to sixteen. So
we should assume that great-aunt is included. So the גמרא Gemara says,
אמר ליה, amar lei, he said back to him, ולטעמיך, u'l'ta'amecha, according
to your reasoning, אי הוי כתיב להיתירא מי היית
סמכת עלייהו? ei havay kativ l'heira mi hait samchat aleiyhu? If let's
say you had seen the list, whatever you saw written, if it
had not said there are sixteen שניות, shniyos, let's say it said
there are sixteen that are permissible, or let's say it said great-aunts
are permissible, you just saw something written like that, would you have
relied on it? דמר בריה דרבנא מי חתים
עלייהו? de-Mar brei de-Ravna mi chatim aleiyhu?
Although you saw this from the list of the house of the
ישיבה yeshiva of מר בריה דרבנא, Mar brei de-Ravna, you didn't see
he signed off on it. You don't know that this is an
authoritative thing that you saw. So the same way you wouldn't have
relied on it to be מיקל meikel because it's not authoritative, so
השתא נמי דכתיבן לאיסורא לאו מר בריה דרבנא חתים עלייהו, hashta nami
d'chtivan l'issura lav Mar brei de-Ravna chatim aleiyhu, so even now that
you saw it said sixteen are forbidden, there's no reason, you can't
base a הלכה halacha on the fact that you saw some random
thing saying that there are sixteen secondary עריות. arayos. You don't know
it's authoritative and anyway you're speculating about what the sixteen are. Alright.
Okay, yes.
First the אמימר. Amemar. Aren't these אמוראים Amoraim rather late to be
debating
this?
Yeah, good question. You know, you're right. I don't know exactly like
I mean it is funny, you know, that you have do have
a late debate about these types of things. Again, one wonders how
much when you get so many generations removed how likely these scenarios
are, you know, people have to be pretty old. Of course, you
could have a case where like a grandfather marries a young woman,
you know, and then he dies and then the woman isn't so
old. Anyway, but okay, it is an interesting point that they are
pretty late. Okay, תנא דבי רב חייא. Tana de-bei Rav Chiya. So
anyway we don't know about great aunts. Okay, so great aunts is
still in a doubt. Now we're going to get the list of
רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya that we just mentioned before that's going to
add six to the list. שלישי שבבנו ושבבתו. shlishi she-bivno ve-she-bivito.
Now this is also going to be a case about multiple generations,
okay? So we basically have the following. You've got your... you have
cases that already start in the Torah to be two generations. What
are the things that are like two generations a problem? You can't
marry your wife's grandmother, your wife's mother or grandmother. You can't marry
a woman and her granddaughter, okay? And you can't marry with also
your own or your wife's, whatever, your own granddaughter, okay? So let's
say you made it both cases great. Your wife's great-grandmother or your
or your own great-granddaughter,
okay? So the grands are already אסור דאורייתא. assur de-oraita. Those are
the few cases that the Torah forbids two generations removed: a woman
and her granddaughter or woman and her grandmother, or you and your
granddaughter. What if we added a generation? So let's take a look.
So that's most of רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya's list. תני רבי חייא
שלישי שבבנו ושבבתו. Tani Rabbi Chiya shlishi she-bivno ve-she-bivito.
Three generations down in your son or daughter, which means your great-granddaughter.
Now presumably if it were just your... remember we said that you
can... אין להפסק. ein la-hefsek. So if it basically just went like
the Torah forbids granddaughter. That's Torah-forbidden, okay? That's אסור assur in the
Torah, that's what the Torah forbids, okay? Now if you kept on
going down, that would just be a case sort of like of
אין להפסק, ein la-hefsek, all daughters, right? But let's say you didn't
do that. Let's say basically what we're talking about... so that's אסור.
assur. Okay, but let's say what you're doing is you have בת
bat and then you have בן ben and then you have בת.
bat. You should have switched in the middle, right? Well, because then
it doesn't make it a direct type of a derivation, okay? It
makes it then then it's a little
bit more distant.
I understand but that's what רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya says, but it's
not as logical because we talked about yesterday that אין להפסק ein
la-hefsek was when it was just completely repeating it just going further
down. This is switching the generations. Or you had a case of
בן בת בת, ben bat bat, or you could imagine בן בן
בת. ben ben bat. Okay, anyway, okay, anyway, but
that's... so this is דאורייתא de-oraita going straight down daughters is a
problem, okay? But this where it's going down to the third generation
but it's mixed, sort of the sons and daughters or whatever, you
know, that's going to be a case where it's going to be
דרבנן, de-rabbanan, okay?
Would it be four generations?
Actually, Michael is a little bit right because if you had a
case about בן בתו ben bito that would also be דאורייתא. de-oraita.
Okay, but anyway, going down those generations is is רבי חייא Rabbi
Chiya's case
which is what, three, is it two and a four, three and
four and five and six? Actually, what when he says third generation,
does he also mean fourth and fifth or does it really just
stop there?
Yeah, that's a good question. I don't think we're going to get
to it, okay? So anyway, in the Torah you have... so in
the Torah you have a case about בן בתו ben bito and
בת בתו, bat bito,
that's דאורייתא, de-oraita, okay? So that's from the Torah that's אסור assur
and presumably if you continue going down with daughters, right, that would
be אסור. assur. But here at this level, at the second generation,
you don't have a דאורייתא de-oraita category. You have בן, ben, right,
your grandson. And then you keep on going down, third generation,
great-granddaughter, but the second generation was grandson. That's what's not so obvious.
That's what he's adding. So if you take a look at רש"י,
Rashi, שלישי שבבנו: shlishi she-bivno: בת בן בנו, bat ben beno, דבת
בנו ערוה, de-bat beno ervah, okay? Or שבבתו בת בן בתו. she-bivito
bat ben bito.
בת בן בתו, bat ben bito, right.
Okay, all right. So here again here it's דאורייתא de-oraita when it's
second generation daughter, so if you continue down with daughters that's going
to be דרבנן, de-rabbanan, but here second generation sons and the חידוש
chidush is when you get to third generations of granddaughters, that's also,
okay? שלישי שבבנו ושבבתו. shlishi she-bivno ve-she-bivito. That's two more that he
was adding, two versions of granddaughters of great-granddaughters.
ושבבן אשתו ושבבת אשתו. ve-she-be-ven ishto ve-she-be-bat ishto. That's very similar, okay?
You also can't marry in the Torah... and this is the same
thing except with your wife. Here's your wife, okay? now these are
children that she has from a different man, but you can't marry
a woman and her granddaughters, okay? So in the Torah... In the
תורה Torah you cannot marry a woman and her granddaughters. There's two
types of granddaughters, either through a son or daughter. Okay, that's what
the תורה Torah forbidden, a woman and her granddaughter. And now if
this were to continue down, right, great granddaughters etc., that's already obvious.
Okay, because at the second generation, it's already biblically forbidden. But what
רבי חייא Rabbi Hiyya adds is when the second generation it's not
forbidden. Second generation is grandsons, okay,
right, second generation is grandsons, okay, and it's not forbidden second generation,
but it will be forbidden third generation. Okay, so wife and great
granddaughters
whether they are coming through a son or through a daughter. Okay.
So basically your great granddaughters and your wife's great granddaughters. If that's
confusing, I was just trying to explain the חידוש chidush because we've
already said אין להפסק ein l'hefsek in some of the cases, but
his חידוש chidush is when at the second generation it's just grandsons,
nevertheless at the third generation great granddaughters it's going to be a
problem whether it's your great granddaughters or your wife's great granddaughters. That's
four more. Just wait, let's finish all six. That's four more, four
versions of great granddaughters.
And similarly שנייה, shnia,
שנייה, shnia, those cases of those four granddaughters, great granddaughters are secondary
עריות. arayot. Okay. רביעי שבחמיו ושבחמותו שנייה, revi'i she-be-chamiv ve-she-be-chamoto shnia, similarly,
okay, if we go up generations. Okay, in the תורה Torah you're
not allowed to marry a
woman and her granddaughter, which means the same way you can't marry
your wife's granddaughters, you can't marry your wife's grandmother. Okay. So you've
got her father, we'll just write חמיו chamiv and חמותו, chamoto, which
is her father and her mother.
Okay. That's אמא ima and אביה. aviha. Okay, if that's her father
and mother, so you cannot marry
her grandmother either on her father or mother's side, right? Everybody with
me? That's grandma. Okay, you can't marry her grandma either on her
father or mother's side. How about going up another generation? Okay, great
grandma,
right? So that's what he's coming to add. Okay, that you cannot
even marry her her great grandmother. Okay, so let's take a look
at that. It says
רביעי שבחמיו ושבחמותו. revi'i she-be-chamiv ve-she-be-chamoto.
Fourth generation, that's funny, you should have called this third generation, but
if you read the way
it's fourth generation going up through grandmother or through or through her
either through her mother or through her father. Okay. Now by the
way, by the way, this again, this might be relatively obvious because
this is just the אין להפסק. ein l'hefsek. The bigger חידוש chidush
that he would be making would be if we were dealing with
her grandfather's mother, right? Right?
So if you're just taking the grandmother and going up a generation,
not so much of a חידוש. chidush. But if it's her grandfather
on either side, then it's a bigger חידוש chidush because then we're
sort of at this generation it's okay, and he's still saying even
if at the third generation it's not an ערווה, ervah, going up
to the great grandmother once will make that will be a שנייה
לעריות. shnia le-arayot. Now you had a question, Michael.
The same point of רבי חייא Rabbi Hiyya you raised,
although רש״י Rashi does say it's all great great grandmother.
Right, but when there's a different gender in the middle, so let's
say a son, right? The grandson, and the grandson's wife, or whatever
it is, I'm trying to think of the mother, that's your wife's
grandson's wife.
Yeah, so you
can marry her, but then if it's a daughter, then you can't,
it's one of those things where she can come to you like
we had yesterday.
That's exactly what the גמרא Gemara did say yesterday, exactly that scenario.
Well, in רבי חייא's Rabbi Hiyya case, but okay, but it's exactly
that's fine. Okay, okay. By the way, רש״י, Rashi, I don't know
why רש״י Rashi says this if he means it דווקא, davka, but
רש״י Rashi actually says we are talking about grandmother's mother. So I
don't know why. To me that's more obvious if it's grandmother's mother.
I don't know why we can't be talking about grandfather's mother, but
if you look at רש״י Rashi that's just the way he describes
it, he says אם אם חמיו. em em chamiv. Okay, or he
says אם אם חמותו. em em chamoto. So I don't know why
he makes it think it could be different. Anyway, you had a
question, no, yeah, you had a question?
If everybody in this scenario is 17 years old and they had
a child,
the
great grandparents will be like 51 years old. Yeah.
How how why would somebody do that? I don't know, people got
remarried for a lot of reasons, economic reasons, other reasons.
Someone in this congregation who had a very elderly grandfather marry a
very young woman and have.
That happens all the time. There you're having a younger man marrying
a much older woman.
Alright, anyway, what can I tell you? No, you can marry, just
won't have kids.
No, no, but I'm saying though we're talking about sixty sixty years
difference.
Yeah, it can happen, so you could get married. Alright, anyway, the
גמרא Gemara says like this. Alright, so anyway, so those are the
six he adds, great granddaughters and great grandmothers.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר ליה רבינא לרב
אשי, Amar lei Ravina le-Rav Ashi, מאי שנא למעלה דחשיב ליה אשתו,
mai shna le-mala de-chashiv lei ishto, מאי שנא למטה דלא קחשיב ליה
אשתו? mai shna le-mata de-lo kachashiv lei ishto? Why when you're going
up do you say four generations, counting the wife as one, and
when you're going down you say three generations, not counting the wife?
Okay, so it's just a question of the nomenclature. So למעלה דאיסורא
מכח אשתו קאתי, lemala de-issura mikoch ishto ka-ati, counting up where your
great-grandmother is forbidden because of your wife, because basically it's your wife's,
you know, it's a woman and her grandchild and her grandchild, so
it starts with your wife. It's how they're related to your wife.
So דאיסורא מכח אשתו קאתי חשיב לה, de-issura mikoch ishto ka-ati chashiv
lah, so it counts the wife as generation one, and then her
grandmother is generation three, her great-grandmother is generation four. But it's your
wife and your wife's grandmother, so therefore your wife counts as generation
one. חשיב לה. Chashiv lah. למטה דאיסורא לאו מכח אשתו קאתי, lemata
de-issura lav mikoch ishto ka-ati, going down where it's not your wife,
it's actually it is when it's talking about you, but when you're
talking about your granddaughter, it's not about your wife. So it's about
your first, you know, your son is generation one, grandson is generation
two, great-granddaughter is generation three. So you start the generations after you,
not including you. לא קחשיב לה. Lo kachashiv lah. So the גמרא
Gemara says: והא בן אשתו ובת אשתו דאיסורא מכח אשתו קאתי ולא
קחשיב לה. veha ben ishto u-bat ishto de-issura mikoch ishto ka-ati velo
kachashiv lah. But you also dealt with your wife's great-granddaughter. So that's
because of the relationship to your wife. So there you should have
called it four rather than three. Your wife is one and her
great-granddaughter, you know, granddaughter's three, great-granddaughter is four. So the גמרא Gemara
says: איידי דתני תלת דרגי למטה דידיה, aidei de-tani tlat darghei lemata
didei, since when we were talking about you, we said three generations
below you, your great-granddaughter, we're going to count with your first, by
the first generation after you, ולא קחשיב, velo kachashiv, and we didn't
count you as generation one, תני נמי ג' דרגי למטה דידה, tani
nami gimmel daragei lemata didei, when we're talking about your wife's great-granddaughter,
we call it three generations below, ולא קחשבה, velo kachashva, and we
didn't count her as generation one, even though she was the source
of, even though it started with the fact about her and her
great-granddaughter's relationship to her. You have a problem with that, Charlie? Makes
sense. It
just... all right. Makes sense. Anyway, okay, we started when we went
down counting after you, and then once we started that when we
dealt with your wife, we also counted the lower generations. When we
went up, we started with the wife as generation one, so that's
how we got it. Fine. Anyway, conceptually it's not such a big
חידוש, chiddush, I mean it's not so hard to understand. What רבי
חייא Rabbi Chiya did is he added when dealing about in a
straight line, he added even, you know, another generation, great-granddaughter, great-grandmother. Okay.
אמר ליה רב
אשי לאבימי מהגרוניא:
Amar lei Rav Ashi
le-Avimi me-Hagronya: שניות דרבי חייא יש להן הפסק או אין להן הפסק?
shniyot de-Rabbi Chiya yesh lahen hefsek o ein lahen hefsek? So just
for all the people that were so bothered about somebody marrying his
great-grandmother, we want to know what about great-great-grandmother? What about great-great-great-grandmother? What
about great-great-great-great-granddaughter? Okay, do they keep on going or not? תא שמע,
Ta shma, דאמר רב ארבע נשים יש להן הפסק ותו לא. de-amar
Rav arba nashim yesh lahen hefsek vetu lo. So רב Rav said
there are only four women that the generation that you don't keep
on going up and down generations and we discussed those yesterday. And
these weren't in רב's Rav list, so clearly... Fine. So exactly the
גמרא Gemara says: so clearly these don't have any, you know, don't
stop, they keep on going. גמרא Gemara says: No, דילמא כי קאמר
רב להאי מתניתא. dilma ki ka'amar Rav le-hai matnita. No, maybe what
רב Rav was referring to the בריתא baraita that listed eight, those
eight, amongst those eight, only four of them stop. But maybe with
רבי חייא, Rabbi Chiya, maybe they do stop. Okay. תא שמע: Ta
shma: שלישי ורביעי. shlishi u-revii. When we when רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya
identified them he said specifically third generation below, fourth generation above. That's
a very specific number. That sounds like only that generation. שלישי ורביעי
אין טפי לא. shlishi u-revii in tefei lo. Only up to three
generations below and four generations above. The גמרא Gemara says: No, דילמא
משלישי
ואילך וממריביעי ואילך. dilma mi-shlishi va-eilakh u-me-revii va-eilakh. Maybe it means starting
at the third generation, not starting at the fourth generation. Although then
it's funny then why would he give a number, why wouldn't he
just say, you know, all the way up, like why give the
number? Why wouldn't he just say, you know, all the...
all the great-granddaughters, all the great-whatever.
Anyway, fine. But the גמרא's Gemara not convinced. Okay. אמר ליה רבא
לרב נחמן: Amar lei Rava le-Rav Nachman: חזי מר האי מרבנן דאתא
ממערבא ואמר. chazi mar hai merabbanan de-ata mi-ma'arva ve-amar. Did you, you
know, you should see that there's a certain רב rabbi that came
from the west, from ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, ואמר: ve-amar: בעו במערבא.
be'ei be-ma'arva. They asked in ארץ ישראל: Eretz Yisrael: גזור שניות בגרים?
gazu shniyot be-gerim?
So we are basically wrapping up now guys. We're done with the
list we had yesterday, we're done with the question about, you know,
mothers, brothers, wife on the mother's side, certain interesting versions of aunt,
we're done we did great-aunts, then we did great-great-grandmothers, great-great-granddaughters, and now
we are in, and now we're done with the list. Now we
have one last question which is how does this relate to converts?
Okay, because somebody converts and they convert let's say with their family,
so there's a principle of כגר שנתגייר כקטן שנולד דמי, kegar she-nitgayer
ke-katan she-nolad dami,
so they're not considered to have any familial relations with the, you
know, their although they're biologically related to the people they were biologically
related to before, they're not considered to be sort of having a
familial relation with
them. Everything, do any of these things apply to גרים? Gerim? Now
the first question could begin even in the biblical עריות. Arayot. A
גר Ger and his sister convert, a גר Ger and his mother
convert, a גר Ger and his daughter convert. So biblically speaking, they
could get married. Okay, but rabbinically we don't allow it as we're
about to see because then it would seem like that, that, you
know, Judaism is less restrictive, lenient, less holy than being a non-Jew.
Being a non-Jew you couldn't marry this woman, now you're Jewish and
you converted together with your sister and you two can get married.
Okay, like I, it's quite funny, you know, somebody told me about
somebody who was converting and he was coming from like a very,
I don't know, certain type of a sect of a, sect, I
don't know, certain type of a strand of Christianity where they and
he was like saying, so is it allowed for you guys to
like, like read Harry Potter? We can't do that where I come
from. He says, oh my God, really? You guys are so lenient
about everything! So,
you know, something about like all the witchcraft in Harry Potter was
like טרייף Treif and was אסור Assur to read. Anyway, what?
I
do some of that too.
Okay, okay, that's her. Anyway, so, so we don't allow the דאורייתא
De'oraita עריות Arayot even though technically it would be allowed because of
the nature of conversion. What about the rabbinic עריות? Arayot? Would those
apply to a גר Ger or not? Let's take a look. Let's
take a look. תא שמע, Ta shema, ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and
he said, בעו מיניה Ba'u minei they asked, גזרו שניות בגרים או
לא גזרו שניות בגרים? Gazru shniyot b'gerim o lo gazru shniyot b'gerim?
Did they make the שניות Shniyot forbidden to גרים Gerim or not?
אמר ליה Amar lei so he said to him, השתא ומה ערווה
גופה Hashta u'mah ervah gufah what about somebody who's a biblical ערווה?
Ervah? אי לאו דלא יאמרו באנו מקדושה חמורה לקדושה קלה לא גזרו
בה רבנן. Ee lav d'lo yomru banu m'kdusha chamura l'kdusha kala lo
gazru bah rabanan. So if it were not that the converts would
say, oh look, we left a holier religion to a less holy
religion because now we can marry, you know, these, you know, עריות,
Arayot, they wouldn't have made it forbidden. So they didn't just say
we're going to just blanket make it forbidden. It was specifically done
because of the concern that it would look like this was less
weighty. So if that's true, שניות מיבעיא? Shniyot miba'ya? Is there any
question that we should make the שניות Shniyot forbidden? I mean, you
know, anyway, presumably the שניות Shniyot would never have been forbidden as
a non-Jew. But a non-Jew would not be forbidden to marry, I
don't know what, I can't even remember the list anymore. Anyway, his
great-great-grandmother, okay? So if he converts together with his great-great-grandmother, great-great-granddaughter, we're
not going to make her forbidden because oh, when I was a
non-Jew I wasn't allowed and now I'm allowed. He was allowed to
do that even as a non-Jew. So the cases that for us
are שניות, Shniyot, right, non-Jews don't treat as forbidden. So therefore there's
no reason for us to make the שניות Shniyot forbidden to a
convert because it won't seem like we're being more lenient. So the
basic answer is yes, they're מותר, Mutar, they're מותר Mutar to a
convert
because technically, technically they're not considered related, but it won't feel like
a leniency to—he'll see that they're being more lenient maybe for himself
than for other Jews, but it won't feel like a leniency vis-a-vis
where he came from. So the basic answer is there are no
prohibition of שניות Shniyot for the גרים. Gerim. Let's continue to the
משנה Mishnah and then I'll take a question. אמר רב נחמן, Amar
Rav Nachman, גרים הואיל ואתו לידן תימא בהו מילתא. Gerim ho'il v'atu
l'yadan teima behu milta. Oh, since we're talking about converts, let's say
something else. Okay, obviously that's somewhat related. אחי מן האם לא יעידו.
Achi min ha'em lo ya'idu. If you have converts who converted, brothers,
maternal brothers who converted, they cannot be test—they cannot be witnesses together
because, you know, again, the idea that they're somewhat still seen as
brothers even though הלכתית Halachikly they're not, so they should not be
witnesses together. ואם העידו עדותן עדות. V'im he'idu edutan edut. בדיעבד B'di'avad
however, if they did testify, it's good because קטן שנולד Katan shenolad
and they're not really considered related. So even though it's a little
bit looks like they're related, we don't want them to testify לכתחילה,
Lechatchila, בדיעבד B'di'avad brothers who converted can testify together and they're not
and they're not considered related.
אחי מן האב, Achi min ha'av, however, if they converted, brothers on
the father's side, paternal brothers that converted, מעידין לכתחילה, Me'idin lechatchila, can
testify right at the outset. Now that's a little bit funny. Everything
we've been learning, relationships on the father's side are more likely to
be problematic than on the mother's side. How come here not? So
the basic answer is because here technically speaking, הלכתית Halachikly speaking, they're
not related at all. קטן שנולד, Katan shenolad, they don't have the
familial relations. But okay, how bad does it look is the question.
And if people are related through their mother, okay, then it's obvious
that they're brothers, right? And if you're related through your father, it's
a little less obvious that they're brothers. I mean, that's the perception,
but you know, there's always an element of doubt and so on.
So the גמרא Gemara says technically they whether, you know, there's no
familial relation, they can be witnesses together. But rabbinically, if they're related
through the mother, they're brothers through the mother, it looks worse. It
looks more evident that they're brothers and therefore we want to, you
know, the biological relationship. Maybe here's even a better way of thinking
about it, which just occurs to me, which is that by the
mother, there's clearly a biological. logical relation. And therefore even after they
convert, it's clear that they're biologically related, right? And therefore, even though
הלכתית halakhically that doesn't mean anything, לכתחילה lechatchila that should be a
problem. They're still biological brothers. People that were had the same father
and different mother or they believe they have the same father and
they had a different mother, their basic identity as brothers is not
so much that they have an obvious biological relationship. It comes from
the fact of their recognition as being part of the same family,
right? You're in the father's house, you know, you're part of the
same sort of social construct of a family, right? So people assume
a biological relationship, but the basic more identity is the social construct
of a family. That more obviously goes away when you convert. So
in the case when, what?
I would say it depends which house you're in.
All right. Anyway, but the point is when the case of the
mother that there's clearly an enduring biological relationship, so don't be testify
together
לכתחילה. lechatchila. But בדיעבד bedi'avad it's okay because הלכתית halakhically that doesn't
mean anything. In the case of the father, there's not clearly a
biological relationship, even לכתחילה lechatchila you can testify. Okay, let's just finish
it up and then I'll take the questions. Well let me just
finish this up, okay, אפילו הכי מן האם נמי מעידים לכתחילה. afilu
hachi min em nami me'idim lechatchila.
Even biological brothers who converted can testify לכתחילה. lechatchila. ומאי שנא מעריות,
u'mai shna me'arayot,
why is it different than the עריות? arayot? עריות לכתחילה arayot lechatchila
we have the איסורים issurim like we said before, for a גר
ger who converted. So we would have said the difference is because
קדושה קלה קדושה חמורה, kedusha kala kedusha chamura, right? Like the גמרא
gemara said before. The גמרא gemara here gives a different answer.
ערוה לכל מסורה, erva lechol mesura, because עריות, arayot, anybody decides who
they're going to marry, okay, and therefore we have to be more
strict. If we start allowing a גר ger to marry his sister,
right, so then other people will think they can marry their sisters.
So we have to be strict. עדות לבי דינא מסורה, edut levei
dina mesura, when it comes to who can testify, that's controlled by
the בית דין. beis din. אגר שנתגייר כקטן שנולד דמי a ger
shenisgayer k'katan shenolad dami ובי דינא ידעו, u'vei dina yadu, right,
כקטן שנולד דמי. k'katan shenolad dami. בית דין Beis din knows that
once they've converted they're not הלכתית halakhically considered related, and therefore we're
not afraid to allow it because we're not afraid that other people
will make a mistake. A mistake about testimony won't happen, it's always
being controlled by the court. So as opposed to before where the
גמרא gemara said the reason we don't let a גר ger marry
his sister is because it will make it seem like Judaism is
more less holy than the religion they came from, here we say
we don't let it happen because it'll lead other people astray. And
therefore we don't have to be concerned in a case of testimony
because that's controlled by the court.
And therefore we can even allow even a maternal brother, brothers, to
testify together as גירים. geirim. Okay, now there were a couple of
hands. That was Charlie, yeah.
So I convert. Then,
actually this is a factual case. I convert, I don't have any
first cousins but I have a second cousin.
Catholic church until very very recently would not have permitted us to
get married. Second cousin.
As a Jew, I could marry even a first cousin. Right.
So קדושה קלה קדושה חמורה.
kedusha kala
kedusha chamura. Yeah, well we don't make new גזרות gzeiros but that's
true. It's true you might have now cases where the religion somebody
came from is more strict even in the שניות shnios area and
we're saying that the שניות shnios are מותר. mutar.
And in fact thirty US states prohibit first cousins, even first cousins
from getting married. Very interesting. And still it's
encouraged. Fine. This is not one of those.
Reuven, yeah, Michael.
With respect to what this last point was saying that if ערוה
לכל מסורה ועדות לבי דינא מסורה, erva lechol mesura ve'edut levei dina
mesura, then that would seem to be an argument to prohibit the
שניות shnios to have been מותר, mutar, right?
Yeah, unless it's a type of גזירה לגזירה gzeira ligzeira type of
a concern. It's true, maybe from this new reason you could have
reassessed the שניות shnios question. תוספות Tosafot works through how come the
גמרא gemara in one point looks at the קדושה kedusha question and
the other case ערוה לכל מסורה. erva lechol mesura. Dov, you had
a question? No?
Yeah, well this point, I was looking at רש"י Rashi about the
לא יעידון. lo ya'idun. So he the way I read it was
as follows: He says כקטן שנולד דמי. k'katan shenolad dami. Then he
says דרוב אחין בגר קורבת אם. de'rov achin bager kurbat em. And
then he says again כקטן שנולד דמי. k'katan shenolad dami.
Right, so he's trying to explain what the לכתחילה lechatchila problem was
with the mother. So I was trying to make it more of
like of a perception issue. Right, but רש"י, Rashi, the קורבת אם
kurbat em means before they've converted. Meaning, I didn't want to get
into it but basically even as non-Jews, right,
so the תורה Torah recognizes relations. The point is once you've converted
it doesn't recognize the family relations, but non-Jews before they've converted, it
recognizes family relations, you know, like one of the שבע מצוות בני
נח sheva mitzvot bnei Noach relates to עריות arayot and so on.
So there רש"י Rashi is dealing with the fact that even though
we've been dealing with that the paternal relationship is more meaningful or
more likely to be a problem, you know, for עריות, arayot, but
for non-Jews the maternal relationship is more significant than the paternal one.
I didn't want to get into that but that's basically what he's
getting at.
So I don't understand the distinction here that ערוה לכל מסורה ועדות
לבי דינא מסורה. erva lechol mesura ve'edut levei dina mesura. Yeah, so
the issue doesn't seem to be what people would make a mistake.
mistake, the issue is, is the גר ger going to, or people
think about the גר. ger.
Right,
that's what I said. I said the גמרא Gemara has shifted what
its concern was. Earlier the concerns were what the גר ger thinks
about the difference of the religions, and here it's about leading to
mistake. So that's why you've got this long תוספות Tosafot trying to
figure out which is the which is the real concern here and
what the implications would be. Last question, then we'll move on. Yep.
So technically, if you married a גיורת, giyoret, you could marry her
mother, at least biblically.
Right. Oh, you?
Yes. You also, the same way a גר ger could marry his
mother, a person could marry a גיורת giyoret and and and her
mother, or her daughter, or whatever. Right. Not according to this, right.
But this... okay. חס ושלום. Chas v'shalom.
But that's actually an interesting point, because then it's not what the
גר ger saying that we went from קדושה קלה. kdusha kala.
It's what you're saying. Yeah.
So this is why which is why the question about what somebody
will, how much the issue of what somebody will say as opposed
to other types of concerns, that's a good point. That gets into
the last issue that the גמרא Gemara shifted the area of concern.
Okay, let's get on now to the next משנה. mishna. Thankfully that's
done now for the issue of שניות לעריות, shniyot l'arayot, not to
say we won't be revisiting things, but now we're moving back, now
you're going to say, 'Oh, can we just get back to יבמות
Yevamot questions?'
Okay, so here's the next משנה. mishna. מי שיש לו אח
מכל מקום,
Mi sheyesh lo ach
mikol
makom,
anybody who has any type of a brother, זוקק את אשת אחיו
ליבום. zokek et eshet achiv l'yibum. So and then this guy Reuven
dies, whoever his brother is, it requires makes Reuven's widow obligated in
יבום. yibum. Now what we're going to see in the גמרא, Gemara,
not to ruin the surprise, that what it creates of any type
of brother or it says any type of son means even a
ממזר. mamzer. So if somebody has a brother who is a ממזר,
mamzer, right, father, slept with a married woman, okay, and he's got
now a brother who is a ממזר, mamzer, that brother still creates
an יבום yibum obligation now to his widow. All right. So and
what we've mentioned even before, the idea that you could have a
חיוב יבום chiyuv yibum with a ממזר, mamzer, you do חליצה, chalitza,
you don't do you do חליצה chalitza to a half brother. Yep.
Could be other cases too. Could be his mother before she could
divorce her husband. You could be a full brother too. Anyway, we
have before a case of יבום yibum with a ממזר mamzer where
we said obviously you do חליצה, chalitza, you don't do יבום, yibum,
but there's still a חיוב chiyuv to do חליצה, chalitza, and if
you did יבום, yibum, it would be effective. Okay, so any type
of a brother makes the woman obligated in so to so to
speak, creates an יבום yibum obligation. ואחיו הוא לכל דבר, v'achiv hu
l'chol davar, and it's fully considered his brother. חוץ ממי שיש לו
אח מן השפחה ומן העובדת כוכבים, chutz mimi sheyesh lo ach min
hashifcha umin haovedet kochavim, unless it's a brother who came from a
from a from a female slave or from a non-Jewish woman. From
a non-Jewish woman isn't considered Jewish, and from a female slave, right,
whatever, quasi, etc., but certainly isn't considered to be related to him.
Okay, we'll see about that. מי שיש לו בן מכל מקום, mi
sheyesh lo ben mikol makom, anybody who has any type of son,
even if the son is a ממזר, mamzer, מכל מקום
פוטר אשת אביו מן היבום, mikol makom poter eshet aviv min hayibum,
exempts his father's wife from the יבום. yibum. Now that's a funny
way of phrasing it. What it means is that the fact that
Reuven had a son, this son might be a ממזר, mamzer, then
Reuven dies, so Reuven's wife doesn't have to do יבום, yibum, because
the only time you do יבום yibum is when the person dies
without a son. Even if that son is a ממזר, mamzer, you
don't do יבום. yibum. Okay. וחייב המכהו והמקללו, v'chayav hamakehu v'hamakalalo,
and if this ממזר mamzer would hit or curse his father, he'd
be חייב מיתה, chayav mita, okay, which is maybe not such a
חידוש. chiddush. ובנו הוא לכל דבר, u'vno hu l'chol davar, and is
considered his son for all purposes. חוץ ממי שיש לו בן מן
השפחה ומן העובדת כוכבים,
chutz
mimi
sheyesh lo ben min hashifcha umin haovedet kochavim, unless it's a son
that comes from a slave or a non-Jewish woman. That's not considered
his son and therefore if the son, hits him, it's not חייב
chayav for hitting his father, and if the and if the guy
dies, there's still a מצוה mitzvah of יבום yibum because he's not
his legal son. Okay, so if the guy dies, even though he
has a biological son and he dies with a biological son, there's
still a מצוה mitzvah of יבום yibum because he's not his legal
son. Now we know the term bastard means born out of wedlock
and therefore not a legally recognized son. That's what it sort of
means in the English language. That's not what ממזר mamzer means. ממזר
mamzer is the product of a forbidden sexual relationship. And what this
משנה mishna is telling you is the only concept of a non-legally
recognized son does not matter ממזר, mamzer, does not matter out of
wedlock, does not matter what איסורים issurim were done, does not matter
if it's a if it's from adultery, the only not legally recognized
son is a son of a non with a non-Jewish woman or
with a or with a slave.
Okay, yeah, Rabbi Lynch, the שפחה shifcha is a שפחה כנענית. shifcha
knaanit. כנענית. knaanit.
Yeah. Okay.
Now the גמרא Gemara says: מכל מקום לאתויי מאי, mikol makom l'atuyey
mai, what does it mean any type of brother? אמר רב יהודה
לאתויי ממזר, Amar Rav Yehuda l'atuyey mamzer, even a brother who's a
ממזר, mamzer, okay, he's has a מצוה mitzvah of יבום yibum to
the for the widow. פשיטא אחיו הוא, Pshita achiv hu, obviously. מהו
דתימא נליף אחוה אחוה מבני יעקב, Mahu d'teima nilef achva achva mibnei
Yaakov, that the brothers by Yaakov say שנים עשר אחים אנחנו, shneim
asar achim anachnu, and we say כי ישבו אחים יחדיו, ki yeshvu
achim yachdav, מה להלן כשרים ולא פסולים, mah lehalan ksharim v'lo psulim,
the same way there, although the we learn there already paternal brothers.
Let's also learn non-ממזרים. mamzerim. אף כאן כשרים ולא פסולים. Af kan
ksheirim velo pesulim. קא משמע לן. Ka mashma lan. So why maybe
we should say the same thing here? So says ואימא הכי נמי,
ve-eima hachi nami, so let's say that. No, כיון דלענין יבום מיפטר
מיפטר, kivan d'le-inyan yibum miftar niftar, so since when it comes to
יבום yibum purposes they are that we're going to see in a
minute that if you have a son who's a ממזר mamzer that
if ראובן Reuven has a son who's a ממזר mamzer and then
ראובן Reuven dies that ראובן's Reuven's wife is exempt so we'll see
that a ממזר mamzer as a son exempts his mother or exempts
his wife's father from יבום. yibum. מזקק נמי זקיק, Miskak nami zakik,
so we see he's enough considered a son within the הלכות halachos
of ממזר mamzer of יבום yibum so therefore he's also enough considered
a brother within the הלכות halachos of יבום yibum to say that
there's still a concept of יבום yibum by a ממזר. mamzer.
הכא נמי בהילכתא דכאילו, Hacha nami b'hilchsa d'ke'ilu,
yeah,
we'll see, we'll see in a minute. Okay, so that's waiting for
us to see how we know that if a son is a
ממזר mamzer it exempts the father, but when we find that out
then we can assume so you see ממזר's mamzer's not excluded and
somehow assuming what's true by a son is true by a brother.
ואחיו הוא לכל דבר, V'achiv hu l'chol davar, and he's fully considered
a brother. למאי הלכתא, L'mai hilchsa, for what הלכות? halachos? So ליורשו
l'yarsho to inherit you, if somebody dies and he doesn't have a
son and then he doesn't have a father whatever then it goes
down to his brothers. Okay, so to inherit.
ולטמא לו, U'l'tamei lo, and if he's a כהן Kohen and he's
got a brother who's a ממזר mamzer and the brother dies he
would still be מיטמא metamei himself in the burial in taking care
of the burial of his brother of his brother. Okay, it does
not say oh he's only a ממזר mamzer I don't have to
no he's still your fully your brother.
פשיטא אחיו הוא, Pshita achiv hu, obviously. סלקא דעתך אמינא, Salka da'tach
amina, הא כתיב כי אם לשארו הקרוב אליו
Ha k'tiv ki
im l'she'ero
hakorov eilav that a
כהן Kohen becomes מיטמא tamei to his flesh that is close to
him. ואמר מר שארו זו אשתו, V'amar mar she'ero zu ishto, and
flesh means his wife because in the פסוקים psukim it never says
that a כהן Kohen becomes מיטמא tamei to his wife. וכתיב לא
יטמא בעל בעמיו להחלו, U'chtiv lo yitama ba'al b'amav l'heichalo, and then
it says but do not become מיטמא tamei to become desecrated by
it. יש בעל שמיטמא ויש בעל שאינו מיטמא, Yesh ba'al she'metamei v'yesh
ba'al she'eino metamei, sometimes a husband is מיטמא metamei and sometimes not.
הא כיצד, Ha keitzad, what's the case? מיטמא הוא לאשתו כשירה היא,
Metamei hu l'ishto ksheira hi, he's מיטמא metamei if his wife is
כשירה ksheira meaning is a woman he could marry. ואין מיטמא לאשתו
פסולה, V'ein metamei l'ishto psula, but not if he's married to let's
say a גרושה. grusha. So the same way a כהן Kohen is
not מיטמא metamei to his wife who's a גרושה grusha maybe he
should not be מיטמא metamei to his brother who's a ממזר. mamzer.
הכא נמי מיטמא הוא לאח כשר ואין מיטמא לאח פסול, Hacha nami
metamei hu l'ach kasher v'ein metamei l'ach pasul, so קא משמע לן
ka mashma lan that no that he is מיטמא metamei to his
brother even if his brother is a ממזר. mamzer. ואימא הכי נמי,
V'eima hachi nami, maybe I should say the same thing? But says
no התם לאפוקי קאימה, hatam l'afukei kaima, if the כהן's Kohen's wife
is a גרושה grusha he should be divorcing her, she shouldn't be
remaining his wife and therefore the relationship is weakened it's not the
problem that since she is problematic there's not something's wrong with her
status you're not entitled to be מיטמא metamei to her. It's not
that she doesn't deserve him to be מיטמא metamei to her because
she's got a problematic status it's because the relationship is weakened. She
shouldn't be married to her is why he's not מיטמא metamei to
her. Okay so here הכא אחיו הוא. hacha achiv hu. Here even
if he's a brother he's still even though even if he's a
ממזר mamzer he's still your brother. So the issue about the woman
who is a גרושה grusha the problem is that she's not fully
his wife, shouldn't be his wife.
Here he's his brother so he's his brother it doesn't matter whatever
his personal status is bottom line still his brother and therefore he's
מיטמא metamei to him.
You could argue the same way he shouldn't be his brother so
to speak because
no but there's nothing that in the yeah but not in some
hypothetical world meaning right now in this world the כהן Kohen and
the גרושה grusha should be getting divorced. Okay here this guy is
always going to be your brother. Yeah.
And in the case that there were multiple brothers who are not
ממזרים mamzerim versus a
ממזר mamzer and then is the ממזר mamzer equal status in terms
of or does he have to wait until the brother actual no
equal status you mean like in terms of inheritance or יבום? yibum?
יבום. Yibum. Oh that's an interesting question the same way we say
like מצוה בגדול mitzvah b'gadol would we say here well since here
the ממזר mamzer is not allowed to do יבום yibum he's only
allowed to do חליצה chalitzah and the other brothers would be allowed
to do יבום yibum I presume that we would start with the
other brothers. I guess it's true let's say if all of the
brothers wanted to do חליצה chalitzah or if we פסקינן paskin
like that מצוה לחלוץ לפני יבום mitzvah l'chalot lifnei yibum which is
a discussion we're going to see would then you sort of say
well as long as we're doing חליצה chalitzah might as well give
it to the older brother and if the older brother's a ממזר
mamzer who cares maybe yes but as long as we're preferring יבום
yibum then certainly the other brothers are going to get precedence. Okay
so the גמרא Gemara says like this חוץ ממי שיש לו אח
מן השפחה ומן העובד כוכבים chutz mi mi sheyeish lo ach min
hashifcha u'min ha'oved kochavim that you're not related to a brother from
a non-Jewish woman or from a slave. So the גמרא Gemara says
מאי טעמא אמר קרא mai ta'ama amar kra הן יהיו. hen yihyu.
Because it says
by a slave that she and her children belong to the master,
not to the father, they're not related to the father. Okay, now
it does not deal with the non-Jewish women which gets back to
the whole discussion we had before about, you know, about matrilineal descent,
that we're going to see later interestingly here, the גמרא Gemara completely
skips over that. Let's keep on going. Take the questions later, try
to get a little further down. מי שיש לו בן מכל מקום
פוטר, mi sheyesh lo ben mikol makom poter, מכל מקום לאתויי מאי?
mikol makom la'atuyei mai? What does it mean any type of son
gets the father's wife out of יבום? yibbum? אמר רב יהודה לאתויי
ממזר. amar Rav Yehuda la'atuyei mamzer. Again ממזר. mamzer. מאי טעמא? mai
ta'ama? And here's what we said is the one we knew, meaning
the brother as a ממזר, mamzer, we learn from the son that's
a ממזר. mamzer. How do we know the son who's a ממזר
mamzer gets his father's wife out of יבום? yibbum? דאמר קרא ובן
אין לו. de'amar kra uben ein lo. He has no son. So
we do a little play on words: אין לו ein lo עיין
עליו, ayen alav, like as read with an עין, ayin, like investigate,
and the investigate telling us that anybody that might count in a
son category counts, which means we don't only learn out a son
who's a ממזר, mamzer, you know what else we learn out? Not
only a son but even a daughter. Okay, so from this דרשה
drashah of אין לו ein lo עיין עליו, ayen alav, we very
much broaden the scope of who could exempt the father, the father's
wife from יבום. yibbum. Okay, okay, so let's take a look.
So that's less a matter of like שם המת, shem hamet, right?
So by the way, if you look at the side, there's an
interesting discussion where it says דרישו Dirshu הערוך He'Aruch בערך עיין be'erech
ayen with an אלף, aleph, not an עין, ayin, עיין עליו, ayen
alav, and it basically says it means like nothing, like אין. ein.
So, which is, I don't know, or which is I guess what
אין ein means. Anyway, but somehow to suggest, I don't know, I
have to take a look at it. But somehow to suggest
it means that there's absolutely no remnant to the father, absolutely no,
you know, descendant. So any type of a descendant would change the
story.
By the way, now not
only a son and not only a daughter, grandson, granddaughter. Okay, so
even though the תורה Torah just says son. And by the way,
since we've been hearing until now that the idea of יבום yibbum
is בנחלה תלה רחמנא, benachalah talah rachamana, you might think that daughter
would be different than son. I understand, that's well, right, once you
get daughters inheriting, but nevertheless, anyway. Okay, so that's שם, shem, an
actual שם, shem, and you think less of a daughter than a
son. Maybe, right. Okay, וחייב על מכתו. vechayav al makato. So therefore
we know that a son who's a ממזר mamzer has a relevance
for יבום, yibbum, and if he hits his father, he's חייב. chayav.
So now this is the one thing that the גמרא Gemara sort
of questioned. אמאי? ammai? קרי כאן ונשיא בעמך לא תאור, kri kan
venasi be'amcha lo ta'or, do not curse a like a, you know,
a ruler in your nation. So and from that we learn so
that's the קללה, klalah, okay, and from that we learn בעושה מעשה
עמך, be'oseh ma'aseh amcha, only if he acts like he deserves to
be in the people, but for a sinner, it would not be
prohibited. And presumably, if that's true about you're exempt for cursing another
person, you'd be maybe exempt for cursing your father if he was
a רשע. rasha.
And since he was a ממזר, mamzer, and
he's a רשע rasha because whatever he did to produce you, maybe
obviously he did a burning sin.
So the גמרא Gemara says, כדאמר רב פנחס משמיה דרב פפא, kide'amar
Rav Pinchas mishmeih deRav Pappa, בעושה תשובה. be'oseh teshuvah. No, like Rav
Pinchas says in another context, we're talking about the person did תשובה,
teshuvah, and therefore, even if he sinned before, right now, he did
תשובה. teshuvah. So הכא נמי, hacha nami, here too, כשעשה תשובה. kesh'asah
teshuvah. So the גמרא Gemara says, והאי בר תשובה הוא? ve'hai bar
teshuvah hu? Could such a person really do
תשובה? teshuvah? דתנן detnan שמעון בן מנסיא אומר, Shimon ben Menasya omer,
איזהו מעוות לא יוכל לתקון? eizehu me'uvat lo yuchal litkon? זה הבא
על הערוה והוליד ממנה ממזר. zeh haba al ha'ervah veholid mimena mamzer.
So you know, so this is the the effects of the sinner
are always continuously around, how could you do a full תשובה? teshuvah?
So the גמרא Gemara says, השתא מיהא עושה מעשה עמך הוא. hashta
miha oseh ma'aseh amcha hu. Look, whether or not he gets full
atonement or, you know, for his sin, whether God wipes his slate
clean, okay, nevertheless, the question here is, is he עושה מעשה עמך?
oseh ma'aseh amcha? Is he right now living a religious life, living
an observant life? So it's not a question about whether, you know,
about how many demerits he has and, you know, how much he's
going to be punished for his sins. The question is, is that
right now is he acting like, as you know, within the context
of the nation or outside of the context of the nation? And
as long as he is now acting correctly, those prohibitions would continue
to obtain. Yes, Charlie. Question.
Back when we you're talking about עבודת כוכבים, avodat kochavim, sounds like
it seems to הגויה. hagoyah.
Right, so thank you, that's worth noting, which is that anytime you
pretty much see עכו"ם akum or עבודת כוכבים avodat kochavim not all
the time but almost all the time, it's a self-censorship. The original
word was usually גויה goyah or נכרית, nochrit, but when the church
started
having apostates tell them about all the bad stuff that is said
about non-Jews in the תלמוד, Talmud, so the and then the church
started burning the תלמוד, Talmud, so the Jews went through a period
of self-censorship where they changed all the times that it said גויה
goyah or נכרית nochrit to עכו"ם, akum, which is idolater, so they
could say, or literally even more than idolater, עכו"ם akum would mean
star worshiper, okay, or sometimes they would say, you know, which is
עבודת כוכבים, avodat kochavim, not just עובד עבודה זרה. oved avodah zarah.
So עבודת כוכבים avodat kochavim is like always a... I don't know,
maybe there's one exception, a self-censorship so they could say, "Oh, we're
not talking about you, we're talking about these ancient pagan star worshipers."
Okay, so yes, so the original text is גויא goya or sometimes
נוכרי. nuchri. All right, let's do a little bit more. תנו רבנן.
Tanu Rabbanan. הבא על אחותו. haba al achoso. What? You think that
worked? I don't know, apparently people say they just...
they stopped burning it, they stopped burning the תלמוד. Talmud.
I mean, maybe even if they didn't believe that's what it originally
meant, but at least they were able to convince them that the
book wasn't as offensive in the form that it was in. Okay,
so תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. Somebody told me they once saw a
סידור siddur said, "מי כעמך ישראל אקום אחד בארץ." Mi ke-amcha Yisrael
akum echad ba-aretz. All right. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. הבא על אחותו
והיא בת אשת אביו חייב.
haba al
achoso vehi bas eshes aviv chayav. So this is not going to
seem relevant, but we're going to tie it back in. Somebody who
has sex with his sister, who also is his father's wife's daughter,
which would be a normal case. Okay, but you could have a
sister that's not
with a woman who wasn't your father's wife. But here it was
both. Okay. והוא בת אשת אביך והיא בת אשת אביו והיא בת
אשת
אביו חייב משום אחותו ומשום בת אשת אביו.
vehu bas eshes avicha vehi bas eshes aviv
vehi
bas eshes aviv chayav mishum achoso umishum bas eshes aviv. You get
two... you transgress doubly. So therefore, if it's like בשוגג, beshogeg, you
would bring two קרבנות, korbanos, or if you were warned, you'd get
two sets of lashes, one for sister and one for father's wife's
daughter. Because you would be... you'd transgress by either of those alone.
You could have a sister who's not your father's wife's daughter, right?
A sister who was born with a woman your father had a
child with who he was never married to. So you have a
sister who's not your father's wife's daughter. And you could have a
father's wife's daughter who's not your sister, which would be your what?
Father's wife's daughter is not your sister? Stepsister. Okay, but stepsister alone,
right, is not... you're not חייב chayav for stepsister unless it's also...
correct. So stepsister by itself is not alone. So you're not חייב
chayav on stepsister unless it's also your sister. So every time... so
the... but the תורה Torah prohibits them separately. So you have one
prohibition which is sister by itself. The other is sister who's also
your father's wife's daughter, which is actually... well, so actually I said
it wrong. So it's not your stepsister. You've got your sister and
then you've got your sister who also is... because who also is
your father's wife's daughter. So it's your actually
your half-sister, half-sister, but the mother at least was married to your
father. Okay, so you would say since in that case when your
father's married to her, since you're חייב chayav anyway for sister, maybe
if your father also happens to be married to the mother, right,
it shouldn't be a new category, maybe it's all just one definition
of sister. That's the debate. So the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says
you're חייב chayav for sister and if your father also happens to
be married to her, you're also חייב chayav for father's wife's daughter.
חייב משום אחותו ומשום בת אשת אביו. chayav mishum achoso umishum bas
eshes aviv. רבי יוסי בר יהודה אומר אינו חייב אלא משום אחותו
בלבד
Rabbi Yose bar Yehuda omer einu chayav ela
mishum achoso bilvad ולא משום בת אשת אביו. velo mishum bas eshes
aviv. מאי טעמייהו דרבנן? mai ta'amayhu de-rabbanan? What's the reasoning of the
Rabbis? אמר מכדי. amar michdi. Let's take a look. כתיב ערות אחותך
בת אביך או בת אמך. ksiv ervas achosecha bas avicha o bas
imecha. It already says don't reveal the nakedness of your sister, whether
your father... whether paternal or maternal. So once it says that, בת
אשת אביך מולדת אביך אחותך היא, bas eshes avicha moledes avicha achosecha
hi, when the verse says... another verse says don't have sex with
your sister who is your father's wife's daughter, למה לי? lama li?
Why did it have to prohibit it? It already said sister regardless
of whether your father was married to the mother. So why does
it again say your sister when the father's married to her mother?
שמע מינה לחייבו משום אחותו ומשום בת אשת אביו shma mina lechayvo
mishum achoso umishum bas eshes aviv to tell you you get two
sets of transgression. That's the Rabbanan. רבי יוסי בר יהודה אומר אמר
קרא אחותך היא. Rabbi Yose bar Yehuda omer amar kra achosecha hi.
No, the verse says when it speaks about that your father's married
to her mother, she's your sister, which means משום אחותו אתה מחייבו
ואי אתה מחייבו משום בת אשת אביו.
mishum achoso ata mechayvo ve'ei ata
mechayvo mishum bas eshes aviv. It's telling you there's only one prohibition
here, sister. There's... it's not more prohibited just cause your father's married
to her mother. ורבנן האי אחותך היא מאי עבדי ליה? ve-rabbanan hai
achosecha hi mai avdi leh? What do they do with the fact
that the verse says it's your sister, what he's reading to say
that's the only prohibition here? So מיבעי להו לחייבו על אחותו בת
אביו ובת אמו mibaya lehu lechayvo al achoso bas aviv ubas imo
to tell you that in a case where somebody is not just
maternal or just paternal sister, but is actually a full sister, you're
also חייב. chayav. Now, cause the תורה Torah says don't marry your
maternal sister, don't marry your paternal sister. What if she's both? Are
you gonna say she's both, she's also one or the other? But
the גמרא Gemara thinks that no, maybe that's a different status. So
we learn out from the extra words אחותך היא achosecha hi to
tell me even a full sister is prohibited. לומר שאין דנים מן
הדין lomar she'ein danin min hadin and you wouldn't have just said
from a קל וחומר, kal vachomer, you needed the extra words of
אחותך היא achosecha hi to tell you a full sister's also prohibited.
רבי יוסי בר יהודה Rabbi Yose bar Yehuda would say back, אם
כן, im kein, if that's all the verse wanted to do was
prohibit a full sister, לכתוב רחמנא אחותך. lichtov Rachmana achosecha. Just say
your sister. היא למה לי? hi lama li? What's the extra היא?
hi? To be limiting and to say משום אחותך אתה מחייבו, mishum
achoscha ata mechayvo, you only transgress a sister prohibition, ואי אתה מחייבו
משום בת אשת אביו, ve'e ata mechayvo mishum bas eshes aviv, there's
no new prohibition because your father was married to her mother. ורבנן,
Verabbanan, and the Rabbis would say back, אף על גב דכתיב אחותך,
af al gav dechtiv achoscha, איצטריך למכתב היא. itztrich lemichtav hee. Even
though it says אחותך achoscha to tell you there's a prohibition of
full sister, it has to say היא, hee, שלא תאמר בעלמא מזהיר
מן הדין. shelo tomar be'alma mazhir min hadin. Really, we could have
figured out full sister based on a קל וחומר. kal v'chomer. וכי
תימא אחותך דכתב רחמנא למה לי? vechi teima achoscha dechtiv rachamana lamah
lee? So why did the Torah have to say full sister? יופי
דאתי בקל וחומר דהא כתב לה קרא. yofei de'asi b'kal v'chomer deha
kesav lah kra. Yeah, I could have figured out full sister, but
the Torah still said it even if I could have figured it
out. But in principle, I can learn out prohibitions from a קל
וחומר. kal v'chomer. So כתב רחמנא היא, katav rachamana hee, so it
wrote היא. hee. No, only היא hee is forbidden because I told
you she's forbidden. Normally you could not learn out prohibitions from a
קל וחומר. kal v'chomer. So basically the Rabbis are saying אחותך היא
achotecha hee is to tell you full sister, and even though I
could have learned that from a קל וחומר, kal v'chomer, I need
a פסוק. pasuk. And רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi is saying היא hee
is telling me the only prohibition is sister, it's no worse just
because your father is married to her mother. One more line, I
know we're a little over, but one more line. רבי יוסי ברבי
יהודה Rabbi Yossi b'Rabbi Yehuda would say, אם כן לכתוב ליה רחמנא
לאחותך היא באידך קרא. im ken lichtov leh rachamana leachoscha hee be'idach
kra. Write אחותך היא achotecha hee by the verse that's talking about
when your father isn't married to the mother. If all the point
of אחותך היא achotecha hee is to forbid a full sister, why
does it say אחותך היא achotecha hee in the verse where it
says בת אשת אביך? bas eshes avicha? So the reason it says
it in the verse where it's talking about your father married to
the mother is to tell you even when the father's married to
the mother, it's not a new prohibition, it's only the prohibition of
sister. Okay, and we'll pick up tomorrow. All of this is to
get to the final line which is: if the רבי יוסי ברבי
יהודה Rabbi Yossi b'Rabbi Yehuda says there are not two prohibitions, there's
only one prohibition in the Torah of sister, it's no different whether
your father's married to the mother or not, why did the Torah
also have a verse about the father being married to the mother?
And that's the reason for quoting this, that's going to tie it
into what we've been discussing. So we'll see that tomorrow.